[Music]
so I really want to talk about the
intellectual dark web which now is
probably nearly two years old since it
was kind of formally unveiled in the New
York Times and the Barry Weiss article
and we've obviously featured the IDW
quite a lot in rebel wisdom we've kind
of looked at it like I was really
fascinated by it from the beginning the
the idea of I think when we first talked
you you said something about how all
truths must align is that you're all
true narratives must reconcile all true
narratives must reconcile so from the
outset I kind of had this idea of could
we have like the these public
conversations where these different sort
of maps of the world for example like
children Peterson's Jungian perspective
evolutionary biology is there a is there
alignment it's a way that these can come
together and there's this sort of sense
of excited say a sense of real
excitement at the beginning some of
those first encounters on the Rubin
report you and Eric Jordan and Ben
Shapiro there's this sort of sense of a
really a live conversation that's going
somewhere new and this sense of novelty
think we call it kind of thinking in
public and I know that we've talked
before about the need for there to be
spaces where people feel comfortable
enough to be honest and that the IDW is
a place where you could actually kind of
manufacture that kind of safety and I
think that's all of that's really really
valuable but I also have this sense that
certainly over the last couple of years
some of that for me there hasn't been as
much novelty and I've also did a talk
recently at a university in America
where I've sort of talked about where I
saw some of the failure points or some
of the places where the IDW didn't
necessarily push on to a new resolution
I'd love to ask a few questions about
that what's your what's your sense of
the trajectory of the IDW and where it's
at now in
20:20 well I have to say to be candid I
missed the IDW I feel like the IDW was a
very interesting dynamic place to be and
it isn't gone but I also don't see it
being active and I must say I'm
concerned about what that means you know
if it's taking a break and going to
re-emerge in some sense then that's all
well and good on the other hand I worry
that the the IDW space did not fully
understand what threatened it and that
the fact that it is it is a quiet space
at the moment might be reflective of
forces we we didn't understand now of
course there's also a certain amount of
happenstance in that obviously Jordan
Peterson has had a health crisis along
with his wife Tammy and that has taken
him out of the public eye for a period
of time and that has obviously had an
impact on the space but it's not the
only thing that that we encountered and
anyway I'd like to see the IDW or some
outgrowth of it return and pick up where
the lively IDW that we remember left off
mmm because this is one other thing that
I've been sort of tracking since the
beginning I think the for me the naming
of the IDW the name of the intellectual
dark web was sort of the coming to
consciousness and I'd love to hear if
you agree with this or you'd have a
different perspective was the kind of
becoming to consciousness of the
alternative media space as an entity in
itself but you had this you had a lot of
podcasters a lot of personalities like
Sam Harris Joe Rogan who become very
popular in sort of growing in the shade
or in between the cracks of the
mainstream media and the naming of the
intellectual dark web was a way of sort
of saying oh it's now a thing there's
actually a thing and there is another
center of power that is distinct from
the mainstream media and it and it
showed up maybe a lot of the flaws and
the things that mainstream media weren't
talking about but also what what I think
we've seen as well as sort of an
evolution of what the expectations are
of of an entity that now has a an equal
or maybe even some in some places more
power than to shape narratives in the
mainstream media does so in a way would
you would you agree with that that it
was sort of the naming of a maybe an
emergent entity that hadn't previously
been named and that's why the name the
intellectual dollop sort of took off and
you saw a lot of it had a strong
magnetic potential well I think
sometimes faulted for always seeing
things in biological terms but I would
argue that almost all the things that I
see that way are actually biology or a
manifestation of it in this case what
you have is a niche space where a
completely corrupt and broken media
apparatus left everybody in kind of a
low level of constant starvation for
anything authentic and decent and
unexpected and certain folks were
exploring that space Joe Rogan pioneered
an entire mechanism for interacting with
that space as did Sam Harris Dave Rubin
was creating an entirely distinct
mechanism of inhabiting that space and
at the point that intellectual dark web
was named by Eric in effect what I think
he was doing was describing a phenomenon
that was quietly evolving in this niche
and the niche is still there because of
course the hunger is still there the
media hasn't gotten any better in fact
it's still playing the same games that
it was playing in 2017 but the question
of what inhabits that space has become
more complicated for various different
reasons I mean one of them simply being
that there is now wide recognition that
there is a space
that means maybe for both better and
worse that there is an economic
opportunity in that space which lots of
economic entities are now trying to
capitalize on so that's now a hazard
that was much smaller a couple of years
ago by virtue of the fact that most
people weren't aware of it and what do
you mean by that what what are you
saying coming in he talked about this
with the idea of the grifter oh no
actually grifters weren't anywhere on my
mind though that's obviously a
manifestation of the same process that
there are grifters who will learn what
messages are resonant amongst the
audience of the IDW and start parroting
them for cynical reasons that's
certainly a phenomenon we've seen but
there's also a recognition amongst very
standard economic entities that there
are I ball x' that are searching for
authentic content of a counterintuitive
type and that many of them have ended up
in IDW space and you know what can we do
with that it's just the simple standard
question that capitalism is always
pointing at everything which is how can
we turn that into a profit and anyway
there's nothing inherently wrong with
profitability but the fact that there's
profit to be made threatens to do to IDW
space what it did to journalism and
anyway I think the one advantage that
our DW space has is that maybe it's
aware that it is supposed to be the
alternative to a broken media and that
offers the possibility of resisting and
how would you define IDW space because
that was another point that I made in
the in the talk was that there does seem
to be a lot of energy and desire in and
certainly around the time when it was
named among a lot of people for good
faith dialogue for discussion of these
kind of issues
and it it never feels like it didn't
doesn't feel like it ever quite went
beyond the the people who were named in
that initial article and became more of
a kind of cultural polar public movement
so first let's talk a little bit about
what IDW space is IDW space as far as I
can tell is a an environment in which
the priority is put on stating what one
actually believes irrespective of the
social consequences of those statements
and of partnering in discussion with
other people on the basis that you hold
the discovery of truth to be a higher
value than pushing your own agenda and I
think the IDW to me it was a prototype
of something and it was a highly
successful prototype the question then
is once you have a highly successful
prototype of discussions in which people
prove that they are capable of updating
on the basis of new information capable
of delivering their own perspective even
if it puts them in jeopardy all of those
characteristics what do you do to bring
others in because now the world is
alerted to the fact that there is
something with a lot of eyeballs on it
so the desire to figure out how to get
into that conversation is very high and
the danger of people entering it for the
wrong reasons is through the roof so you
have to solve the question of how to
broaden the discussion so that it
remains dynamic and adds new elements
without killing it by virtue of opening
the doors and the so called quality
control dropping through the floor and
there has to be some way of making the
conversation
modular so that failures do not take
down the space itself and I'm not sure
we figured out the answer to that
question yet I would love to see the
problem addressed but I think at this
moment where we are as we've seen a
beautiful proof-of-concept we've seen
that people resonate with it that it
solves a problem that there are lots of
things that could be said amongst
members of the IDW things that need to
be said that are still difficult to say
in more mainstream circles and to the
extent that people can bootstrap a
conversation that is more capable more
dynamic more honest and live to tell the
tale we need to foster and I mean one of
the things that I've noticed as well is
that if this is more of a web-based
insurgency and I'd say that it probably
is the failure conditions online are
very different from the failure
conditions of the mainstream media
mainstream media you get a groupthink
you get kind of the fact that everyone
is kind of coming from the same
universities they're all in the same
environment on the coasts what I see
different in in the online space is this
idea that almost the platform's
themselves are weaponized because you
know by going on a certain platform
you're exposed to their audience it's
like you've got a comment thread
underneath every YouTube so every single
platform there seems to be subject to
these very centrifugal forces pulling to
one side or the other and that for
example you have on one side you've got
someone like Sam cedar who like you can
just see they're sort of beating up on
Dave Rubin and beating up on Sam Harris
and beating up on some of these figures
because they know that's what their
audience wants but you have very
different failure conditions in the
online space like and you can feel that
gravitational force of the audience
especially on on YouTube which sort of
for me leans right because often those
kind of perspective and not given space
in the mainstream media like this is
something that's really I think worth
pulling apart what would what do you
make of that it's almost like you've
sped
some of these failure conditions for for
online media well at some level were
damned every which way I think one of
the things about social media space the
positive thing about it was that it
allowed something like the IDW to happen
and for there to be an awareness of just
how resonant it was imagine for a second
a world in which social media existed
but YouTube videos did not have a
comments thread tweets did not have a
measure of how many people had resonated
with them or passed them along right
then the IDW would have been mocked as a
insignificant unsuccessful group of
self-important whatevers the fact that
so many people responded to it the fact
that on tweets from members of the IDW
would you would get hundreds or
thousands of people responding
positively when if you go to the you
know the anchors of a major news program
you'd find ten or twenty at most
indications of interaction that said
whatever is going on here this is
actually an important social force it
can't be ignored
you can throw epithets at it you can say
it's a gateway to the alt-right or
whatever other kinds of nonsense were
tossed around but you can't say that
it's falling flat and so my point is yes
the tendency of social media to create
gravitational forces that pull people
who are living in that space in one
direction or the other that's a very
dangerous phenomenon and it's even more
dangerous if the directions people are
being pulled in are not organic if
something decides to use social media to
pull people in some direction they
wouldn't otherwise go that's very
dangerous so it is critically important
that people in that space figure out how
to think independently of their
audiences so if their audience begins to
pull them in sumter
that's not really of their organic
belief they don't go and they accept the
social cost of not going but not having
the feedback that comes from people's
organic interactions online is even more
dangerous in my opinion so we've got
sort of audience capture on the one hand
and lack of feedback and the ability to
snuff out promising things by pretending
that they're not reaching anyone those
are two alternate failure conditions
it's interesting to see those those two
sides because I can remember when I
think with either you or it might have
been when I talked to Eric originally
about the IDW the idea was that these
people would be immune from some of the
failure conditions of the mainstream
media because they had their own
platforms they were small operators but
for me that feels kind of naive because
you're going to be subject to the whims
of your audience you're going to realize
what your audience won you're going to
give them what they want to some degree
so there are going to be new failure
conditions for online media that and
I've been like critical of Dave Rubin
quite a few times in the past as being
for me kind of the the obvious example
of that recognizing what the audience
wanted and then kind of just giving them
more and more of that Sam Harris on the
other hand has sort of very delivered
because he talks a lot about Islam he's
kind of recognized that he's sometimes
getting kind of some bigoted people
following him and he sort of very
careful to try and throw them off as
much as possible by talking about how
much he dislikes Trump for example if
there's a whole new set of kind of
ethical and failure conditions that come
in as being a media personality in this
sort of new online world and I guess
what do you make of that and how do you
personally respond to that well there is
a characteristic that a very small
percentage of people have which i think
is disproportionately important in this
space and it is a deafness
to social gravity and it is a
willingness to endure
social harm for a cause or a truth and
so to the extent that I'm looking out
across this landscape if somebody does
not demonstrate this capacity even if
they're saying something I resonate with
they're uninteresting to me because I
know it's only a matter of time before
they get sucked into some gravity well
around some social truth that isn't deep
on the other hand if somebody is
essentially immune to the epithets if
somebody will go down with the FIP you
think well I know this to be true and if
the whole world disagrees with me that
doesn't make it any less true so
therefore you're not going to get me to
to claim anything else then that person
is interesting because they are
independent so I think the IDW space
brought forward a number of people who
have this unusual characteristics to a
highly unusual degree I don't think it
was everybody who was associated with
the space and there is this danger but
in general I think the lesson or the
meta lesson of IDW is that that
characteristic is disproportionately
important as society becomes false and
so the reason that the hunger was so
great the reason that the resonance of
the IDW was so great and the discovery
of the process that unfolded in the
couple of years after was that we need
to figure out how to cultivate this
ability to say what's true when it's
awkward when it's socially damning and
that we also need to figure out how to
value and promote people who have that
characteristic so that they do find
their way into mainstream media for
example because in a way in the social
media environment with all content
creators anyway so being able to say
something that's going to get you mobbed
on Facebook
is probably liked by your friends and
family and people close to you it's
probably a process that a lot of people
have gone through which is maybe why a
lot of people resonated with the IDW
because on some will have a lot of
people feel that they have skin in the
game on this because we've all got the
chance of being kind of socially morbid
or excluded or shamed humiliated on
social media I think that's true many
people have had the experience and I
think it's very disheartening if you
come to the conclusion that having been
mobbed you must have been wrong you must
have made an error and seeing people who
reject that and live to tell the tale or
actually end up looking good because
they resist the mob that's a very
positive lesson for people so you know
the amount of gratitude that flowed from
people seeing successful resistance
against the nonsense was quite rewarding
sometimes I will look at a tweet before
I post it and I will think yeah that
one's gonna get me in trouble that's
going to be costly or I know there's a
certain fraction of my audience that is
going to rebel against that very idea
and probably walk away and then there's
also you know the next thought is yeah
but do you believe it
should you not post that tweet because
you think people are gonna walk away and
then the next thing is quick you post it
because you know you're in a dialogue
with yourself do I want to be captured
by my audience no I don't and that means
that if my not audience needs to hear
something that I believe even if I'm not
looking to convince them necessarily I
just need them to know that somebody
that they considered reasonable actually
holds this belief which they do not hold
and they think no reasonable person
holds that thing needs to be stated and
so the willingness to endure the cost of
stating that which needs to be
is again incredibly important and the
difficult lesson is that the reaction
the rebellion is very concentrated and
the reward if it comes at all will be
delayed it will be diffused it will be
difficult to detect what it's about but
when people see you again and again say
stuff that somebody needed to say even
if they disagree with it the best people
will respond positively today whether
they agree with you or not so we
mentioned at the beginning something
you'd said about all true narratives
must reconcile and I wonder whether I
personally had too much so the IDW one
on one level was showing that people of
different perspectives could have come
could have meaningful conversations that
meant that they weren't falling out they
weren't becoming polarized they weren't
though they were still able to be
friends at the end of the day but my
hope beyond that was that there might be
some shift there might be some kind of
public changing of mine public evidence
of this kind of process of thinking that
then led towards this all through
narratives reconciling and I was I have
been quite disappointed not to have seen
that from the IDW conversations we can
talk about what why that wasn't the case
but do you think it was a naive
expectation that that might happen or do
you think it was a missed opportunity I
don't think it was either I believe in a
sort of fractal hierarchy of timescales
and there are things which we detect on
very short time scales which are
important if somebody changes their mind
inside a conversation it's very dramatic
if they change their mind over the
course of six months or a year it's
still fairly dramatic if it takes four
years it's much more subtle and harder
to track and I'm tracking all sorts of
conversations that I was participating
in over the last several years and I do
see them moving so there was a
discussion between Brian Greene and and
Joe Rogan recently in which they were
discussing
their views on religion and I don't know
what Brian Greene's position was several
years ago but I know Jo's because I
spoke to him about it on his podcast and
he was he had moved substantially I
don't know if to realize that but he had
moved substantially in the direction of
what I think is now becoming a
mainstream understanding which is that
religions may be literally false but
they evolved for a reason they exist for
the very fact that they served our
ancestors now we haven't gotten publicly
to the next phase of that discussion
which is what is their status all right
and I'm afraid that's going to be a
difficult one but I've seen people on
both the religious side move in the
direction of a adaptive explanation for
a religious belief and I've seen people
on the atheist side move in the same
direction so if you're tracking that
conversation broadly you do see the
movement if you're waiting for somebody
to acknowledge a transition over some
short period of time you often don't
detect it so what I would say is what we
really need to figure out is what our
benchmarks are what can be stated in
2020 all right if that benchmark in the
same place in 2020 to have we back slid
have we made progress are we capable of
saying difficult things in in a wider
space in that period and my feeling is
I've seen the conversation move in a
positive direction I've also seen the
backlash intensify but the movement in
the positive direction is clearly there
if you're paying attention to to certain
hallmarks one of the things that I've
also seen and I'd love to get your take
on it cuz I know that this is one of
your phrases that bad faith changes
everything in a conversation this seems
like a very interesting point like the
conversation that
bad faith good faith because it's often
used and I've seen it used often now as
a way of sort of policing who can take
part in discussions who you're willing
to have on your show for example and
there seems to be no obvious definition
like bad faith is almost always
something that someone will say about
someone else but it will never be no one
no one would accept that description of
themselves so how can you define bad
faith in good faith and how can you know
whether and how do you know if that's
being used erroneously as a way of
keeping someone out of the conversation
who should actually be part of the
conversation it should challenge you in
some way yeah it's a good question I
would say a couple things one there is
an issue with certain parameters that
they fail at the point you attempt to
operationalize them so to the extent
that good faith has value in
conversation it may be true that just
simply recognizing that there is
something even if we can't be certain if
we detect it that there is a state and
we can define it and that that state
ought to distinguish between your
viability and a conversation and the
need to bar you from it so I would say
loosely speaking good faith not as
lawyers used to term because it has a
very particular definition as a term of
art in the law but in common parlance I
would say the the sin qua non of good
faith is whether or not a person is
acting with reference to the goal that
they state in other words if somebody
says this is my objective and then they
say something or take an action with the
earnest belief that they are actually
moving towards that objective that's a
good faith even if they're wrong even if
what they're doing is monstrous just the
simple fact that they are telling you
here's the objective and then the action
matches the objective what people do
that is not in good faith is they
provide a misleading objective that's
the easiest place to mislead and
they pretend that their statements or
their actions are actually an attempt to
reach that objective when really they're
an attempt to reach some unstated
objective so can you detect this yes you
can detect it can you do so absolutely
reliably no but if you have enough data
on a particular individuals behavior bad
faith becomes evident over time because
believing in X could not possibly result
in these statements and behaviors which
are counterproductive with relevance
with respect to the the objective so you
know bad faith emerges can you detect
bad faith suddenly can somebody do
something that calls your attention to
the likelihood that they're acting in
bad faith yep you can definitely see it
could you be mistaken that can happen
also but that will also become clear
over time so what I would say is
somebody who is sensitive to tracking
the match of a model to the actual
manifest behavior can see these things
and it's actually not unlike what we do
in animal behavior animals non-human
animals they never tell you what they're
up to right you have to be able to
figure it out based on the fact that you
have a model this is what I think the
animal is trying to accomplish and then
if I watch the animal continuing to
behave its behavior matches that
objective or here's what I think is
happening and then no actually what it's
doing wouldn't make any sense if that's
what it was trying to accomplish so it
must be trying to accomplish something
different this is the same thing it's
basically ethnology versus ethology so
in this context I guess that the key
distinctions we're making in sort of
conversation is are you oriented towards
truth or I Orin - winning winning the
interaction and making the other person
look bad well I have that be a key
distinction we haven't done I have no
problem with somebody somebody is not
inherently acting in bad faith if
they're trying to win and make the other
person look bad as long as they
acknowledge that that's what they're up
to right but if somebody says look I'm
much more interested in discovering the
truth than winning and then they behave
like somebody who's more interests
winning than discovering the truth
that's bad faith it's the mismatch
between the objective and the apparent
objective and the stated objective so I
don't really have any interest in
participating with somebody who's just
looking to score points but the
challenge that they are acting in bad
faith really depends on the fact that
they don't admit that that's what
they're doing
I guess the complexity for me is that
very few people are actually a lot of
people who think they're acting in good
faith and get very upset if you say no
you're about you're a bad faith actor
genuinely don't know or can't tell that
that's what they're doing like oh
probably we could probably come up with
two or three names of people who would
be very very upset if you said you're
actually a bad faith actor and genuinely
believe that that's that they're
actually trying to kind of approach
truth and would argue that's what
they're trying to do so how do you get
past this just being a subjective
judgment by someone who maybe doesn't
want to engage well first of all let us
be clear I think a lot of people make
the error that because they believe
their motives to be positive that that
is the same thing as acting in good
faith and the problem is it's very easy
to rationalize behaviors that are
harmful to others and to paint some sort
of positive spin on them so it's not a
question of whether your internal
motives are decent that's an important
question but there's too much room for
rationalization for us to figure it out
but really a mismatch between your
stated objective and the objective
revealed by your behaviors is certainly
reason for a red flag this also means
that you have an obligation to search
your own mind to discover if in fact
there's a rationale for your behavior
that you're not aware of or only dimly
aware of and you're keeping it out of
your own sight in order to prevent the
knowledge of it from causing you to be
guilty of bad faith
but a person who is willing to search
their own mind and say look I don't know
for sure I'm a human being which means
that most of what goes on in my head is
invisible to me too
but to the extent that I check my own
motives it's not that I'm privately
aware of something and pursuing it and
not telling you about it as far as I
know what I'm saying is my actual belief
and it is based on the things that I've
told you it's based on now what we do
with the difference between the abstract
question does bad faith exist it
absolutely does does something else
exist that we might call good faith it
absolutely does can you detect these
things from the outside yes but it takes
a pattern right what do we do with the
accusation so we've got the personal
fact of acting and good or bad faith
we've got the suspicion by somebody else
based on a pattern of behavior and then
we've got the accusation which might be
used to keep somebody out of a
discussion and the problem is we can't
convict somebody of bad faith unless
there's really substantial evidence that
they're stating an incorrect motive that
they have reason to know that that's
what they are doing or if they don't
know that they've been avoiding it so as
not to know right those are are the
issues but we never have or almost never
have the level of proof that would exist
for convicting a person of a crime for
example did you commit the crime the
evidence says beyond a reasonable doubt
that you did right that's something we
can prove but when we're talking about
your internal motivation it's much
harder to prove and so as a bar we have
to understand that we are not really
claiming the right to exclude somebody
from a public good but in a conversation
I'm not participating in a public good
I'm participating in a conversation
who's very natured
the ability to exclude that which is
counterproductive if I suspect somebody
is acting in bad faith and I don't want
them in a conversation that I'm
participating in and the point is well I
don't want to participate in that
conversation if that person is present
so my participation is contingent on
those that I suspect are not acting in
good faith not being present for it you
don't want to watch that conversation
don't watch it all right this isn't like
I'm saying that person can't come into a
public park because they're acting in
bad faith I guess the other question and
this may sound very naive but is it
always necessary to exclude those who
can you suspect might be bad faith or
might sometimes be bad faith from
conversations or go on one level why not
have the conversation with them and call
it out in real time and let the audience
make out the nines how that can be
useful but I would say there's a simple
question of opportunity cost I don't
have time in the rest of my life for
even all of the conversations I might
have with people who are very careful
about their own motivations and very
earnestly motivated to do positive
things in the world there's just a limit
on how many hours there are left should
I spend some of those hours engaging
with people who are being deceptive
about their own beliefs maybe maybe I
well sure I would I'd be willing to do
that but then I wouldn't exactly bar
them from a conversation if my purpose
was to expose their bad faith I would
agree to participate in it so on rare
occasion it may make sense to have those
conversations but in general the ability
of a person acting in bad faith to snarl
a conversation so that it goes nowhere
productive is much greater than the
ability of somebody acting in good faith
to establish what's really going on in
somebody else's head or that there are
charlatans or whatever so we should
spend our time where it's productive and
in general my experience tells me that
interacting with people who are acting
clear good faith is far more productive
and I know that I know that from both
you I know that both from your
perspective I'm from Eric's perspective
I mean your background is evolutionary
biology Eric has got a background in
physics the IDW as a concept was
actually a part of a much broader
perspective of there are all of these
now there are many narratives in society
we're stuck on many different vectors
and many different perspectives and the
IDW was actually sort of the the public
face of that conversation was kind of
the media branch of that conversation
and obviously quite an important part
because it's the sort of sense making
part that maybe then has a reflection
all these different levels where do you
feel that we're at in terms of shifting
that broader conversation let me see if
I understand what you're getting at
there is a false narrative and a control
over what gets discussed that manifests
in various different places people may
have seen my recent portal episode with
Eric in which we talked about the
question of telomeres senescence and
cancer and in particular we talked about
the issue of the evolution of long
telomeres in laboratory mice which has
tremendous implications for among other
things drug safety testing that question
is clear it's been on the table for many
years and as far as I know it's
unaddressed by the field why I don't
know but the the pattern that becomes
apparent is that every field has bodies
buried under some set of floorboards and
deep insiders know where those things
are and they do not get discussed in
public and the those of us on the
outside suffer whatever consequences we
do as a result of the fact that these
fields are not owning up to what they
know IDW was a manifestation in a sense
of a certain set of issues that were
being
poorly discussed in the Academy and in
media space and it was composed of
people who were willing to pay the price
to discuss what was really going on in
these fields I don't think the fields in
general have gotten any better but what
has gotten better is that the awareness
in the public that something seems to be
wrong across the board that whatever
mechanism we are using the way the
market plugs into our academic fields
and our media environment and our courts
is not resulting in a pretty good
description of reality on which you can
mostly depend which is what it pretends
it's doing it's resulting in a really
crappy representation of reality on
which you cannot depend so the fact that
in 2017 1819
you have mobs of people challenging
folks who are saying things that
obviously have truth in them as if those
people were speaking diabolical untruths
that results in independent minded
people standing up and saying no you've
got it wrong right I don't care what
you're peddling but you you don't have
it right and so the the witch hunting
that became common started to surface
people who in the face of a witch hunt
would not back down
and those people turned out to represent
interesting perspectives from inside a
number of different fields and other
places in society and what they had to
say about what went on internally in
those spots was I open now I'd love to
see it continue and to go further
because to be fewer we don't know the
half of what we've got wrong and we are
suffering all sorts of negative
consequences for what we don't know and
one of the one of the things that
happened initially there was a real
flood of interest in the space
in two in particular in dialogues
between some of the sort of core members
of the IDW and one of the the places
that that published a lot of that sorry
one of the places the hosted a lot of
those was Pangburn originally how and
then Pangburn for those who don't know
had a kind of very public implosion an
event they were going to do in New York
didn't happen but at some of the events
that they were going to do in I think
New Zealand and Australia also didn't
happen a lot of people didn't get their
money back because of that Australia
Australia event did happen the New
Zealand Defence was cancelled and New
York event was cancelled and there were
a lot of people who didn't get their
money back there was a lot of how
important do you think that failure by
Pangburn was for this sort of what felt
like a real trajectory towards kind of
in-person event it's a lot of
high-profile encounters between some of
these the IDW members and that seems to
have tailed off almost completely after
Pangburn failed how important do you
think that was to the trajectory of the
of the IDW unfortunately I think it was
tremendously important there was
something that Pangburn was doing which
was resulting in thousands of people
showing up in one place to see
conversations that nobody knew what the
outcome would be and that was very
healthy the way Pangburn explored that
space was very destructive because
effectively and I don't really know
exactly what he was doing but he
appeared to be gambling
he would create events and then see if
they filled and if they didn't he would
cancel them and he would depend on
future events to produce enough money to
create refunds and so there were some
events that were cancelled that people
did get refunds for and then there was a
point at which the business model
collapsed and refunds stopped coming
that was very costly to
the IDW that the reputation of this
space was jeopardized by that reckless
behavior and I resent it
because it did have that impact with
that said because Pangburn effectively
showed how big the space was I'm
perplexed by the fact that something did
not swoop in to pick up the ball he had
dropped had that thing happened I think
we would still be seeing interesting
conversations and in fact what
conversations we are seeing would
probably have changed over time and they
might be you know just as dynamic and
interesting and surprising today as they
were a couple of years ago but that
didn't happen and there have certainly
been some events since but you're right
the interest in what was going on in the
space and who disagreed with whom and
where the state of their conversation
was that thing has been atomized and now
exists in much smaller forms now that
said there are other things emerging in
the space Eric and I now have separate
podcasts that have emerged in the space
and they definitely don't serve the same
purpose as having you know a theater
full of people there for a discussion
between between IDW members but in any
case my hope is that the momentum that
existed when those events were happening
will be picked up by other things
hopefully some of them will be events
and some of them will take other forms
and if things go well then our DW space
will morph but it will it will continue
and would you I mean as you say both you
and Eric now have podcasts which i think
is a really positive development because
what I also saw from the initial
IDW formation was slight imbalance
because your your your essentially then
some some of those IDW members had ways
to get their message out others had to
be mediated by other by the platforms
do you think that was one sort of
failure condition for it as well the
fact that you were dependent on for
example Ruben Rogan Sam Harris for
actually getting the messages out I
think I'm not really sure I mean it's
hard for me to see that as a negative
because in my case you know I end up on
Rogen's program four times I was on Sam
Harris's program Ruben's program three
or four times in any case it wasn't an
impediment for me to get my message out
because they were interested in having
those conversations what has to happen
now in order for the discussion to self
catalyze I'm not sure and certainly
having more venues as potentially good
you know and it is also true that the
venues that existed are morphing and
changing and I'm not sure what the the
outgrowth of it what I would say is
probably the most important thing is for
the space to be dynamic that at any
point that it becomes a thing that
continues to deliver the same sort of
value it will become boring and that
that wouldn't be positive so I'm hopeful
that a dynamic phase two emerges what do
you think like dynamic phase two looks
like well I think one thing I hope to
see our events that focus more directly
on not just the brokenness of our common
narrative but on particular things that
have failed in quadrants of our
larger discussion so for example I'm
going to be having a debate with david
sloan wilson very soon about group
selection versus what i call lineage
selection and the trouble with this
event is that most people don't realize
how much rests on the outcome of that
discussion it can seem kind of dry and
academic but when you realize that
what's really under discussion is why we
behave in the collaborative way that we
sometimes do and why that fails and that
basically if you want to live in a
civilization that achieves the
objectives that a highly collaborative
civilization might then you need to
understand what it is that the driving
force behind that collaboration is based
on because it's a key feature of the
architecture so in any case i'm hoping
that more discussions like that will
happen where we confront a very narrow
issue on which a great many a great
breadth of things depends and that
people will begin to realize that that's
that's where the rubber meets the road
it's all well and good to find heterodox
thinkers who are bold enough to speak in
public it's another thing entirely to
confront questions on which civilization
hinge rebel wisdom was set up to make
sense of the world at a deeper level
than the mainstream media it was built
for these times of crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times more
films and also for our rebel wisdom
members weekly sense making calls with
our amazing interviewees and also we're
introducing the wisdom gym a place to
practice some of the skills that we've
talked about on the channel thanks for
watching and see you soon
[Music]